Guide to the Erasmus Hall collection ARC.230
Brooklyn Historical Society
Erasmus Hall collection
1787-2000
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.230
0.4 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and three oversize folders.
The Erasmus Hall collection includes documents, ephemera, and publications from Erasmus Hall Academy and Erasmus Hall High School.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
BHS accession 1977.377 was the gift of Mrs. A. Lloyd Lott, 1946. BHS accession 1978.113 was the gift of Alma Uhlitz, 1974. BHS accession 1978.193 was the gift of Kranzt, Landau, Lieb and Nostrand, 1978. BC accession 2009.0015 was a transfer from the Queens Library, 2009. BC accessions 2018.0001 and 2018.0020 were purchased from Brian Merlis.
Historical Note
The first school to be chartered by New York State, Erasmus Hall Academy was founded as a private school in 1786 by Dutch settlers in the town of Flatbush in Kings County (the present-day borough of Brooklyn). The Academy's original building was built on land donated by the Flatbush Dutch Reformed Church the following year. The Academy was deeded to the City of Brooklyn in 1896, after which it became a public high school named Erasmus Hall High School. From 1905 to 1939, four adjoining buildings were constructed for the school around a central courtyard, and the school's original building underwent restorations in 1936, 1952, and 1987. As of 2011, the school continues to be a part of New York City's public school system, and is located at 911 Flatbush Avenue. It is now the second-oldest public high school in the United States.
Sources:
Taylor, B. Kimberly. "Erasmus Hall High School and Academy of the Arts," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 382.
Related Materials
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Historic American Buildings Survey photographs of colonial era buildings in Brooklyn, 1940 (V1974.044)
Brooklyn Yearbook Collection (BCMS.0031)
Brooklyn High School Newspaper Collection (BCMS.0030)
Art Seidenberg collection of Prospect Park and Erasmus Hall High School postcards (2017.013)
Lenore Schwartz school records (2017.010)
Ruth S. Harley family papers (2000.013)
Isobel Sokolow photographs (V1990.017)
Chronicles of Erasmus hall, 1906 (379 B87 C)
Notable alumni of Erasmus Hall High School, 2015 (373.74723 N)
An architectural history and adaptive use plan for Erasmus Hall Academy, 1986 (LB3221.J64)
Scope and Contents
The Erasmus Hall collection is arranged into two series: Erasmus Hall Academy (1786-1896) and Erasmus Hall High School (1896-). Series 1: Erasmus Hall Academy includes a typescript copy of the Academy's certificate of incorporation from 1787; an account book listing all students and tuition payments from 1787 to 1792 and treasurers' accounts from 1819 to 1875; receipts for tuition payments and insurance policy documents dating from 1865 to 1869; and original and copied land records from 1787 to 1896, along with other materials. Series 2: Erasmus Hall High School includes images, ephemera, publications, and documents from the school.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series by institution and time period. Within each series, the arrangement is roughly chronological.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Separated Materials
Some duplicates and original news clippings were discarded.
School lands |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Deeds; Land titles |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Insurance policies; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Account books; Receipts (financial records); Certificates of incorporation; Accounts
- Series 1: Erasmus Hall Academy, 1786-1896
  - Account book, 1787-1875; 1978.113 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Alma Uhlitz, 1974.
    Scope and Contents
    Lists all students and tuition amounts paid (1787-1792) as well as treasurers' accounts (1819-1875).
  - Lease [modern copies], 1797; 1978.193 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    These items and the two indentures of 1861 and 1893 were the gift of Kranzt, Landau, Lieb and Nostrand, 1978.
  - Commercial course receipt, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Land indenture, 1861; 1978.193 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for payments of courses and insurance policies, 1865-1869; 1977.377 (Box OS-6)
    Gift of Mrs. A. Lloyd Lott, 1946.
  - Debating club notes, circa 1880s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Catalogue, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centennial materials, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Land indenture, 1893; 1978.193 (Box OS-6)
- Series 2: Erasmus Hall High School, 1896-
  - Images and postcards, circa early to mid-20th century (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Glass plate negatives, 1900-1910 (Box 2)
    Clubs, sports teams and graduating classes.
  - Commencement programs, 1904, 1907, 1920, 1922, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Event programs, 1905-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1905, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1983 letter is from Mayor Ed Koch to Mrs. Mindy M. Turkenitz of the Special Education Department.
  - Class Day programs, 1907, 1924, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 125th anniversary materials, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Includes an anniversary publication and a pageant postcard set with nine of the original 11 postcards.
  - Clipping about student riot, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Class photograph, 1932 (Folder Flat File)
  - Erasmian magazine, 1935, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 150th anniversary materials, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    The diploma was awarded to Frederick Kraushar and the certificates for achievement in Spanish and English were awarded to Judith Wagman.
  - Sing materials, 1956-1957 (Box OS-6)
    Includes front page and clippings from The Dutchman, 1956, and a photocopy of a Sing button from 1957.
  - Erasmus Hall Museum, 1966, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bicentennial materials, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)